hello everyone it's October 14 2022
we're in
meeting 20. we're in our second
discussion of Chapter eight we have a
few
topics and points in chapter eight and
then maybe we can
preview some chapter nine and have a lot
of space for any other thoughts or
questions people are having so
we can jump to the questions and look at
the um
written chapter 8 questions or does
anyone want to
suggest a point for us to go to
last time we know that some of the areas
we wanted to pick up on
involved learning and hierarchical
modeling and hybrid modeling
one question that came up I think
here but maybe we can revisit is the
Birdsong model
is widely pointed at as an example of
how communication is modeled in active
inference or for active inference
entities
however it's quite literally singing
from the same hymn sheet and the turn
taking is based upon uh joint
expectation of that song being sung that
way
and then the actions that the birds can
take the kind of turn taking that they
enact
is
against related to whether it's like
well somebody has to say it is it going
to be me or is it going to be that
so how do you think we would broaden
that scope
of communication to account for
situations
where there isn't a pre-scripted song
how do other Frameworks for
communication
cybernetic ish or otherwise
deal with
the semantics of conversation
improvisation
open-endedness in conversation
uh actually I had a
somewhat more general question about uh
the bird songs and its relation to uh
this particular systems that they've
developed in the textbook uh you see
some researchers believe that I'm sure
you're much uh qualified to talk about
uh this than me but
there are lots of research going going
around about the territorialization uh
function of bird songs so if we take
that as uh if we take a birth song as uh
as its territorializing mechanism at
least one of uh it's territorializing
mechanism uh can we
somehow
put the dynamic I mean the dynamic
boundary of the markup blanket uh I
think would be affected uh from this
point of view and then
I'm not sure how that would translate
into this specific model if we take that
Dynamic nature of the mark of blanket
boundary
yeah I guess I would just build on that
and say that um the communication serves
a purpose and so
um I think a model shouldn't incorporate
what that purpose is
and how it's served by the communication
and then whether it happens to be you
know syncing up with some predefined
pattern or or whatever is is a is a
follow-on consideration
the generative model in the singing from
the same hymn sheet
is like is very much like the sheet
music example
provided in the textbook
there's a known sheet music script
such that even when there's like a error
in the playing of the music
still the sheet music can be heard
so
just coarsely
what generative models
um I think it's pretty straightforward
to see how a generative model could have
the notation or the sheet music
and then use the sheet music as its
prior
to kind of converge reality
to what extent is communication that way
is it totally disparate and differently
structured or is it a little bit like a
hybrid like you're doing inference on
the sheet music that they're about to
say and then you use your inference
about what they're about to say to
converge what they do say
well you ask a good question which is
well what are some alternative
Frameworks and um
I I know I I know I know some or should
know some and I they're not coming to
mind what comes to mind uh most
immediately in this example is a phase
lock loop in electronics which is simply
a way of synchronizing one circuit's
oscillation with another
and um this is like a phase lock loop
with a bigger vocabulary
so figure out where we are in the in the
pattern and then
um
synchronize with it
and um
but to the answer the question of what
other Frameworks
um
I mean there's
this whole field of
um conversation analysis
um which
um well it feels actually called CA
conversation analysis and they have
identified patterns of
um how people communicate
through a certain
structure of I guess we call them
rhetorical devices for achieving the
purpose of the conversation so the
purpose of the purpose
of the communication is kind of Bedrock
but um and there are multiple purposes
some of which are instrumental some are
which are you know social
um
and then they have identified patterns
for the way human conversation tends to
proceed which are culturally influenced
you know there's some cross-cultural
aspects but then there's certain
different cultures that have different
takes on it so they identify things like
okay now we're in the conversation
opening phase now we're in a phase of
turn where we're exchanging information
and we have turn taking now we have
Notions of
um epistemic leadership or epistemic
authority
um you know who's who's the person who's
asking who's the person who's answering
or taking those uh those roles in the
conversation and and there's certain
rhetorical stances that are taken then
we have so
um that's a pretty well worked out
um I I don't I guess even formalized
system because they you know there's
just there are um you know well
identified patterns um it's it's not
strictly worked out because it seems
like every domain a conversation analyst
goes to and every every group has their
own kind of flavor of it but it is kind
of um
uh it it does have this aspect of
synchronizing
with respect to the underlying known
patterns of each of the parties in a
conversation
the bird song is also oh Ali please
uh sorry adding to what Eric just
mentioned uh that reminds me reminded me
of the uh a much mechanism on a much
much smaller scale
namely the scale of cells and so on uh
and uh particularly the model proposed
by Stuart Kaufman because
um he talks about the
pluripotent nature of cells and how they
communicate with each other uh in the
context of phenomena of induction
biological induction and uh I mean uh in
the embryological development stage of
the cells uh almost all cells are
pluripotent and they're capable of
becoming any of the different types of
cells which characterize the adult
individual so
um that also the the uh from Kaufman's
model perspective
uh these kind of uh inductive signals or
so to speak communicative signals
between cells can act as a kind of
non-specific stimulus
which switches cell among a variety of
internally available stable States uh so
uh I mean a cell
or let's put it this way the basic idea
in this model is that the regulatory
genes within a cell form a complex
Network in which genes uh interacting by
their products can turn one another on
or off you see so uh yeah these patterns
exhibit the kind of homeostatic
stability associated with attractors of
the systems so uh I think that
translates perfectly into this scale as
well this is small
yeah the
the mapping of communication as
generalized synchrony
may be compatible with a variety of
communication mechanisms
and so it abstracts us from the media
of communication per se
because we can talk about the
informational synchronizations
between for example the two internal
states of the two entities
or multilateral synchronizations with
environmental States or so on
um
like thinking about
um the basic mechanics Bayesian physics
the synchronizing metronomes
they don't have a hem sheet they don't
have sheet music
their embodiments
and coupling
um
enables
synchronization
now one thing I might know you know you
I think you asked a good question here
which is you know how would you transfer
translate something like um
um conversation analysis
you know a human conversation into an
active inference model so
um but that that um
kind of reminds me that the continuous
valued
um models
because they're limited by these by what
you can do in these differential
equations
they seem to be fairly simple
whereas if I were to do something like
thinking about human conversation in
terms of active inference I would want
more something more a very highly High
dimensional or multi-state type of
system where I can
um
have more complex
um patterns
and they may not make these you know
Loops these Volterra Loops or something
called Volterra is that right or is this
is Lawrence
something Dynamics yeah
yeah so it may not make those continuous
Loops but I that you'd still get
um
um you know good structured patterns out
of discrete
um systems so I've I'd kind of be
curious I think this chapter would be
because if it what had if it had a um uh
something about communication and
synchrony pattern synchrony but in terms
of discrete value
um active inference models as a
continuous valued ones
yeah
yeah very interesting like
that's what I was wondering which is why
is communication it is
um
continuous time models are argued to be
a natural fit for motor control
our communication
situations Naturally Fit for one or the
other
seems like I know you could imagine it
either way and then also like
um the synchronization means the
internal state of one creature should
come to resolve the uh resemble internal
states of another A Primitive kind of
theory of mind I think
um not as a um uh
fatal critique
but these examples put the rabbit in the
Hat
a little bit too keenly like the
planning example we explored wasn't
truly planning it was like a
parameterized
um Subspace
where single step optimization
emulated planning now one could argue
that they believe that that's actually
like a better approach than than true
explicit planning but that's not what
was on the um cover and then similarly
theory of mind though qualitatively may
be a framing for communication
we're talking still about the bird song
where they have the same shared a priori
generative model
so this doesn't
um in other words theory of mind is is
um is axiomatically and implicitly
embedded within this model
rather than active inference being used
as uh in a priori first principles to
generate some realized computational
theory of mind
I feel like yeah yeah it's like um you
know another aspect of this the The
Continuous solute formulations is
there's really not that many degrees of
freedom
but when you're communicating you know
anything other than a fixed song there's
a lot of degrees of freedom and um
that's why we have symbol systems but
simple systems is where you would use a
discrete model framework for not a
continuous value
okay
let's talk about hybrid
models discrete and continuous models
and learning and updating so these are
two features chapter eight
is
um
within a continuous time framework
just like chapter seven
layered in
these kind of patterns or archetypes of
discrete time models
in chapter 8 analogously
the most
kernel continuous time formalism is
introduced with movement control
and then we're going to see some kind of
extension extensions or
um
patterns
like design patterns that include
continuous time
this is the message passing
okay so missing line here
but we have
here this top half
is like the bottom of figure 4.3 or at
the top I guess discrete time
so we have B Matrix as a transition
Matrix we have discrete time
and we have
um yeah it's discrete time t plus one T
minus one but within each
time point
we see the continuous time you know e
whatever we want to call this
motif
where the B transition Matrix and
discrete time is
functionally substituted
with a derivative map
such that rather than actually uh retro
or forecasting
State values through time this is much
more like a Taylor series approximation
where extrapolation from the presence
under the auspices of slower changing
causes V which play a functional role of
policies
higher derivatives capture more and more
variants further and further from
the origin
what is the ETA
doing
it's playing some functional role to G
again allowing for a line here
in the sense that it is
selecting policy
but it's not it's not policy that's
being selected or discussed this way but
these slower changing factors that
influence how the derivatives are made
but is
you know a free energy variable
let's just ask
okay
what do people think about this type of
hybrid modeling
um how does this
align with
the previous Decades of analog digital
signals engineering
and the interfaces the digitalization of
analog noise and signals and um so on
foreign
well um
I'll only offer one thought if it's all
right
um
so
one of the things that active inference
let you do is look at
a past trajectory
and figure out how to interpret it
in terms of your your variable your
state variables
um
so you can essentially you you look for
the
the probability distribution over
variables that optimizes the free energy
and that allows you to look back in time
and
um
reinterpret
um evidence because you get something
new and it you get you know in light of
new evidence and then some of the
earlier chapters they had this kind of
example and they had the example of the
of a dynamical a dynamic programming
kind of a a model for this so I would
expect that to be the case also in
communication
um systems and I guess I'm going back
again to communication where uh to some
extent you're able to reinterpret what
you thought you heard before
um you know we it's kind of rare in in
language but it happens there are Garden
Path sentences
um
but usually you know you most
communication systems try to be
relatively hierarchical in that once you
was once you interpret your continuous
value signal then you don't leave a lot
of ambiguity you kind of you know fix on
that and then you have to deal with it
later and sometimes you go back and do
repair
so I'm wondering if this figure 8.6 if
that allows that kind of Dynamics where
um you know you're kind of tracking
something in the continuous value level
you're tracking a signal why effectively
by making predictions of what you're
going to hear uh What You observe
um and then can is that able in this
framework to go and influence the symbol
level the uh the B you know the s
s variables above and how far back in
time is it able to do that
nice
that makes me think about phonemes down
here
and audio
and then here are the um
spellings so in a language or someone is
speaking unclearly or you're not super
familiar with the language
um
then you really are like doing inference
on the on the whole time series like
it's like that kind of
um retro casting which can include even
revisionism and and delusions and false
memories and all that now casting
including the tension between
representing things quote as they are
versus like
um having delusions in the present
and then anticipation which of course
hasn't even happened unless you have a
vision of time as you know
something that always was or
however
so
it's really
um
interesting that although this time T is
an index
we are doing inference across these
and maybe it would speak to some
um measure of information processing
and memory and anticipation
the extent to which
um
like meaning
is able to be
the closer meaning is to a critical
point like the more this graph structure
if someone says but I was just kidding
you would want that to apply to to be
like oh I didn't know I was in a
parenthesis and now that they were just
kidding about that
um
so it's actually like delineating those
structural markers
and then reinterpreting meaning
is
perhaps moving towards the kind of
linguistic
modeling
so yeah to come back to it
so this could be a waveform
the observables down here could could be
just a four-year analysis or or a pure
auditory
um waveform
yeah I think phonemes is a that's what
comes to mind also
okay
foreign
motor tasks
so selecting a Target location and
using motor Behavior functionally eyes
to foviate the Target
figure eight seven okay figure eight
seven
is a hybrid or mixed generative model
higher level is this is kind of like the
decision making motor active inference
Fusion
here we have a little bit of the italics
and bold
um
which we could dive into but don't need
to do so at this moment
so you know my recollection for last
week was that that corresponded to
um generative model versus process model
you think that might map again here I
know you didn't want to dive into it
yeah
all right
I believe it does let's just remind
ourselves where it came up earlier in
the chapter yeah it was the very
beginning
right here yeah with italics versus
process in bold model in italics
so eight seven
so now here
the um discrete model is on a time
period of 200 milliseconds
continuous model operates continuously
um I think this speaks to how
biological knowledge can be
encoded in the model structure
I mean a more comprehensive approach
would have done parameter sweeps for
what the optimal number of milliseconds
is to do a discrete model on
however one could say like well the
physiology that we're interested in is
accomplished with a gamma
EEG cycle the gamma EEG cycle is this
many milliseconds
so we're just going to treat
that as like a discrete Rhythm like one
can imagine if the discrete time were
one millisecond here
you would be losing computational
advantage and you'd be kind of like over
slicing
because if eye movement does happen on a
time scale of
hundreds of milliseconds
discretizing to one millisecond is going
to be too fine and discretizing to one
second is not going to enable multiple
actions to be taken within that frame
so time scale and spatial scale of a
system
might be able to be encoded
at the phase of its construction
or structured learning more generally
gaussian mixture model
and the hierarchical
yeah so before before we move on just
about the isocades
um I don't understand what is deemed by
an active inference model for this I
mean why not just say you got a
controller yeah it's a control Loop and
that's good enough
yes
in
um live stream number 50 which we're
just preparing for it's like very
classical cybernetic control Loop
homeostatic Dynamics
and um
it's interesting to
ask like again what makes the model Act
of inference
one could say that if there's a Markov
blanket but we're you know between every
one of these variables
it is a model of action and perception
like so many other models of action and
perception
so what is being shown here is it that
the single imperative the free that
energy-based imperatives
just speaking narrowly here
can mediate
decision making in discrete continuous
Hybrid models
and that it's possible to have
a categorical decision-making model
in feedback
with A continuous ocular motor model
at the very least it places this type of
model
within the
domain and grammar of active inference
modeling
okay data clustering we may have touched
upon also a hierarchical gaussian filter
that I know some people have
worked on
okay let's look at some of the summary
advances in continuous time models
synthetic bird song we talked about this
ocular motor delays
conditioned reflex
that's okay so this is in the chapter
this is in the chapter
I don't know about this exact paper
perhaps but ocular Motors in the chapter
and smooth eye Pursuits
conditioned reflexes that is in this
chapter the blank the conditioned and
the unconditioned to stimuli
building on the Songbird model but the
Songbird model was in 2015.
false inference from sub-optimal prior
beliefs
can but prior beliefs be sub-optimal
um sorry uh actually McPherson has
talked about bird songs uh before 2015
in uh one of his papers I think from
2013 or 12 uh yeah it's it's from 2013
which is co-authored with uh his son I
guess Dominic aphriston so yeah I mean
2015 paper was not the first paper the
name of the paper is the is the free
energy formulation of Music generation
and perception thank you
thank you yeah
wow yeah good um find a reminder
interesting
looks very much like the textbook you
know opening quotes
I can see how this is relates here
researching too
okay
oh maybe even 2009 bird song chaotic
attractors wow you know
it's 10 10 plus years on
the bird song
paradigm
okay so um
deviations in perception
more eye movements
it's kind of fun like how we've talked
about babbling and that across different
domains like cicading
no there's the ocular motor cicade but
are there other kinds of cicadings
[Music]
um
for example I think that
Knowledge Management
niches facilitate semantic cicading yes
enabled by visual cicading as well
because you have to be like looking
around on the page but it's just like
what was chapter four
okay okay that's what we're talking
about chapter four
what's notation I think it's just sort
of like
the analog to scanning around a little
bit
conversational analysis that's you know
that's a very important topic is topic
control
and um or you know if you're uh
if you look at um any you know most
conversations have multiple threads
going
so it's like a Fugue in you know Bach
okay you know which voice is this are
you you know every note is in a voice
and the voice has got some topic and
they intertwine
in girdle escherbach
Prelude Aunt fugue
nice this is very um interesting I think
it starts to
[Music]
um
plant some seeds towards again semantic
cicading computational conversation
analysis and generation
adaptive knowledge environments
like visual accessibility is
one topic you know if somebody has um a
visual difference then making sure that
they can see it is the enabling system
but let's just assume that we're within
a space where we can talk about what is
being seen so then
um how does someone get a clear picture
of what we're talking about
that would be through some sort of
cicade
where you'd recognize
um more uncertainty at the periphery
and um like the fovea in this case is
paying attention to the conversation
and that's why like with a language
we're unfamiliar with we get a little
bit lost because like our circuit was
too slow we don't have the fluency to
cicade and so the video is moving too
fast
to track
so we're just kind of like randomly
listening and like trying to like
compute
but what if somebody were on a guided
cicade journey through their semantic
landscape
I mean just to take this a little bit
further um
this is also maybe uh you know it's a
critical element of
uh cognitive architecture which is the
ability to topic switch and you know in
Psychology and cognitive science we
there's this notion of executive control
and one of the fundamentals of executive
control is to be able to
topic switch so you're on some task you
get an interrupt you have to put that on
a stack deal with your interrupt then
when you're done and maybe the interrupt
is a goal it could be a sub goal it
could be some other topic that comes in
something you have to deal with then
when you're done you have to be able to
pull that back push that back off the
stack
and get back to where you were so all
that that context switching is really I
mean there's measures of how people do
this and there's debates about whether
people can can multitask or not whether
they're actually really multitasking or
they're just multi-threading but they're
there's they're dividing the amount of
computational process by the number of
processes you have going so you're
actually not doing multiple things at
once as effectively as if you just stuck
with one so
um yeah anyway and then it's like do we
have that Intel hyper threading capacity
is it a virtualized hyper thread
on one thread
are there actually different threads
yeah I mean the conversation analysis
other than us being right in the thick
of it and it being highly engaging
supported area let's just continue
through this cases here
action observation
okay mirror neurons
this may be very much related to the um
bird song
seeing from the same hymn sheet or
whatever and then like you know doing
the same dance okay attention
this is a super fascinating area
and um
I think a lot of notebooks and and
applications
like just taking a trace of somebody's
browsing on Wikipedia or across websites
and then reconstructing components of
their generative model based upon their
salience revealed choice is a huge area
and then doing again that with the
ocular motor with webcams
uh and doing it with uh
semantic landscapes
hybrid modeling self-organization
arguably with some
pretty interesting advances in the last
several months and days from Fields 11
others
on the
and four stage earlier but on the
morphogenesis as Bayesian inference
okay
in our last
few minutes here
let's just look ahead to nine because I
think this is setting us up well
um
okay
model-based data analysis or databased
modeling or however we want to say this
is about
parameterizing
structured models with observations
so rather than just by Fiat dictate
saying this is the structure of the
model and it spits out observations like
so and so we want to be able to actually
run it backwards not as a generative
model but as a recognition model
so to speak in this expectation
maximization framework and parameterize
our generative model from sparse or
dense observations and that's also
called parametric empirical base
because you're parameterizing the prior
based upon the mean and variance and
patterns of some empirical data
okay the metabazian approach
Bayes theorem
this may even be something
that could be introduced earlier
even though it's also meta
this is like the the map territory
fallacy fallacy
graphical abstract
which is we're making a map here's Us in
the bigger box even though there's a
dashed box even Beyond us
we're making a map
of a cognitive entity
in its map making of its generative
process
and that was the subject also of some
very rich
discussion several days ago with Jacob
and Ali and Dalton
Ollie anything to add on this
uh no nothing much but
um
uh one General comment I wanted to make
about uh chapter nine is that uh you see
because of my project that I've been
working on for the past several months
this chapter nine has been quite helpful
in developing some of my ideas around
how to uh how to exactly model my
um
am I I mean the music emotional
recognition system that I've been
working on but I wanted to point out uh
one small caveat here uh which is that
uh you see at least in my opinion
chapter nine or uh this so-called model
based data analysis uh it's not a
conducive to
generate
every I mean on every model that's been
described throughout the throughout the
book I mean it's just focused on some
specific kinds of models so it might not
be generalizable to every kind of model
that we've seen throughout all the
previous chapters
good point some
models might be just plug and play
so to speak and other ones might take a
little bit more work to get to use
empirically
okay let's just continue in our last
minute so scan through so metabasian
process we're drawing inferences about
an inferential process
it's a key
point and that's the two levels of
mapping it's like the map of the map
variational LaPlace
variational Bays
factorized
models
for computational Simplicity and
interpretability
based upon the sparsity of coupling of
variables in a base graph
and LaPlace
using a parabolic approximator
of the mode and a variance
to ensure
a simple optimizable heuristic
not that it perfectly recapitulates the
shape of the posterior which doesn't
have to be inverted quadratic
but the LaPlace approximation
is smoothly optimizable for both the
mode and the variance
and here's where they mentioned that's
the parametric empirical Bayesian
approach
and basically LaPlace approximation can
be thought of as making a commitment to
um the quadratic form
so choosing the family that your prior
is going to be of and then bootstrapping
your initial prior
with your observed data
bootstrapping not in the resampling
sense but in the starting oneself out
sense
um this was explored more
in other
works
but you have some likelihood function of
all the parameters L of data
and
optimizing action
involves Computing beliefs about policy
such that policies are proportionally
taking up slices of the pie
monotonically
with respect to their free energy
and then there's a Precision on action
parameter
where you can turn it all the way down
to sort of like don't know don't care
where even large differences in free
energy between policies get equilibrated
out
that's like hot decision making and then
absolute zero decision making would be a
policy that's even 51 percent more
likely
would be always selected
so
the variational free energy expected
free energy it's abound on surprise
due to Jensen's inequality and evidence
lower bound and all this other work in
variational inference
and then that
pie slicing
can be
tuned up or down with a shaky hand
parameter
soft Max temperature parameter
if the Soft Max is one
the pie is undistorted
if the Soft Max is large
you have a Relentless bias
for better policies
or it could be less than one
here's some technical details of the
LaPlace approximation
parametric empirical base
generalized linear modeling
#spm
here's recipe so this is kind of like
chapter six but now it's model based
data analysis collect behavioral data
maybe the data's already been collected
maybe there's some data sets that we
already already can use
formulate a pmdp
I wonder if this is as chapter six not
as chapter 7.
it could be chapter seven as well if
it's discrete time
specify likelihood
perhaps we can um in the coming weeks
check out SPM mdp vbx
and they mentioned the scripts
data this is nice
this will be fun
chapter seven I mean it is the correct
if they're using this type
four
chapter seven chapter four
so
this looks pretty cool pretty
interesting we could walk through some
examples
false inference
computational pathology
so it kind of ends like chapter eight
with a table of references and a summary
so it's a pretty short chapter
and
has some formalisms
but it's only from page 179 of the PDF
to
196. so it's less than 20 pages
and the next chapter I think is the
longest chapter in the book which one is
chapter 10 chapter 10 197.
yeah that one's over 30 pages
but it ends on a high note
um
all right well
interesting
conversations thanks for this
we will come
um back to chapter nine
look through it and then peep into 10.
go through 10 and really solidify our
understanding
of the map and I guess indirectly of the
territory
and then for those who want to join
will probably continue the discussion
and um especially start looking towards
those project ideas again like we talked
just a little earlier about making a DOT
zero
um
a DOT zero sessions for the textbook
so I I have to apologize I'm I'm
traveling for a few weeks so I'm gonna
miss the next
um several sessions
it's all good thank you Eric
um any other comments people want to
make or I'll close the recording
okay
thank you